Guide to the Brian McGinn Papers AIA.015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Brian McGinn Papers
1574-2006
1986-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
McGinn, Brian, 1946-2005
AIA.015
26.33 Linear Feet in 18 record cartons, 14 manuscript boxes, 1 folder in a shared oversized flat box, and an oversized flat file
Brian McGinn was a scholar of the Irish Diaspora and author of articles on this topic. The bulk of the collection consists of McGinn's working papers that are comprised of photocopied sections of books, articles, pamphlets, monographs, handwritten notes, bibliographies, lecture notes, and government records concerning the Irish and their migration to various parts of the world. There are photocopies of colonial records and diaries written as far back as the 16th century, as well as articles and correspondence through 2004. The collection also includes correspondence with other scholars of the Irish and Irish Diaspora and various archivists and librarians concerning research material.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection consists of the working papers of Brian McGinn, a writer and scholar of the Irish Diaspora, whose particular interests were the Irish in Latin America, the West Indies, early colonial America and Canada, as well as those Irish who served with American forces during the Korean and Vietnam wars. The collection is divided into several series. Series I includes articles and other items authored by McGinn and some personal papers. Series II-X are organized geographically while Series XI and XII pertain to veterans of the Korean and Vietnam wars, including documentation on granting of posthumous citizenship to several soldiers.
The files consist mainly of photocopies of articles and sometimes books, as well as bibliographic information used by McGinn in his research. Folder dates often correspond to the original date of photocopied items to give the research an idea of the source material McGinn used. Many photocopies are of original texts from the 17th and 18th centuries. Original correspondence, either letters or email, is included with some files are are photographs and maps of certain areas of study. Many folders in the Korean and Vietnam War Veterans series also include photographs of individuals and these folders are identified.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Archives of Irish America received the collection in the Fall of 2005. The Archives had previously contacted Brian McGinn at the suggestion of historian Kerby Miller, and then negotiated directly with McGinn concerning the collection. The collection was packed by the McGinn family and shipped by McGinn's widow following his death.
The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1997.012 and 2012.057.
Arrangement
Collection is divided into twelve series.
Series I: Personal Files and Published Work, 1976-2004
Series II: 18th Century Irish in New York, 1763-2000
Series III: 16th and 17th Century America: Early Irish in America, 1574-2003
Series IV: 18th and 19th Century Irish in the United States, 1912-2005
Series V: Newfoundland (Nova Scotia, Canada), 1888-2004
Series VI: Leeward Islands/Montserrat, 1642-2002
Series VII: West Indies, 1711-2002
Series VIII: Latin America, 1826-2004
Series IX: Europe, Asia, Africa, et. al., 1825-2002
Series X: United Irishmen, 1787-2000
Series XI: Korean War Veterans, 1948-2003
Series XII: Vietnam War Veterans, 1966-2005
Files are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Historical/Biographical Note
Brian McGinn (1946-2005), was an Irish American scholar and writer who studied the Irish Diaspora in such diverse places as Latin America, the West Indies, early colonial America, Mexico, and Canada. McGinn was born in New York City to Irish immigrant parents from Monaghan and Sligo. His parents were active members of Irish American organizations such as the Ladies Auxiliary of the United Irish Counties Association and Gaelic Football Clubs. After his mother died in 1951, McGinn and his sister returned to Ireland where they were raised and educated. In 1964, after completing high school, McGinn returned to New York and worked for the News Bureau of LIFE Magazine while attending evening classes at Hunter College of the City University of New York (CUNY).
McGinn was drafted by the U.S. Military in 1968 and served as an intelligence specialist at Fort Bragg in North Carolina. From 1969 to 1970 he served in Vietnam on assignment with the 519th Military Intelligence Battalion and was awarded the Join Services Commendation Medal. After being discharged, he completed his BA under the GI Bill and returned to Time-Life in 1972. He moved to Virginia with Time-Life Books in 1976, working as a staff writer and editor. He later became a freelance contributor to various publications, such as Irish Roots and Irish America magazine. In 1979 he married Mary Moran, of Co. Mayo. The couple had a son, Michael.
Later in his career McGinn began to study the Irish in the Korean and Vietnam Wars. As a Vietnam veteran himself, this topic had personal meaning for him. He was also involved on a collaborative website about the Irish in Korea with Marilyn Knapp Litt (http://www.illyria.com/irishkor.html) as well as another site "Irish on the Wall" (http://www.illyria.com/vn_irish_names.html) referring to the Vietnam Veterals Memorial in Washington D.C.
McGinn earned an MA in Latin American Studies from Georgetown University and published extensively on the history of the Irish in Latin America. In addition to the Irish Roots and Irish America magazine, he wrote for newspapers and magazines such as the Irish Times and the Irish Echo's IE. McGinn died on July 20, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Appraisal
In 2021, one record carton was deaccessioned from the collection. The box contained commercially published books and scholarly journals.
Jamestown (Va.) -- History; Virginia -- History; Roanoke (Va.) -- History; Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Montserrat -- Emigration and immigration; Korean War, 1950-1953 -- Veterans -- United States; Korean War, 1950-1953; Latin America -- Emigration and immigration; West Indies -- Emigration and immigration; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Veterans -- United States.; Saint Patrick's Day.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Black-and-white photographs.; Newfoundland and Labrador -- Emigration and immigration -- History; Veterans -- United States; Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, Irish.; Clippings (information artifacts); Articles.; Cemeteries -- New York (State); Ireland -- Emigration and immigration.; Mexico -- Emigration and immigration; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Casement, Roger, Sir, 1864-1916.; United Irishmen
- Series I: Personal Files and Published Work, 1976-2004; 1.32 Linear Feet in 26 folders in 1 record carton, 4 folders in a legal sized manuscript box, and 9 folders in a second legal sized manuscript box
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains articles, correspondence, and other items authored by Brian McGinn. The contents of this series include photocopies of articles and sometimes books, as well as bibliographic information used by McGinn for his research.
  - Bibliographies, Correspondence, 2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notebooks, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Amazon Irish", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "America's First Irish Visitor: Richard Butler", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The American West and Civil War Through Irish Eyes: The Photography of Timothy O'Sullivan, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Articles - BJMc, 1993-2004 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Articles: BMc Montserrat, 1995-2005 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - "The Blakes of Montserrat", 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Bravery and Betrayal in Bolivar's War", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brazil: Abei/Bloomsday - Irish in Brazil Articles, undated (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - "A Century before the G.A.A.: Hurling in 18th Century New York", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Che Guevara's Irish Blood: The Lynch Family of Argentina", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - The Irish At Home and Abroad, 1996 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - "How Irish is Montserrat?" [3 part article], 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Irish in Brazil", 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Irish in Korea" in Ducas (Newsletter of the Irish American Cultural Institute), 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 11A)
  - Irish in Montserrat: Lecture, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Irish in Tidewater Virginia", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "The Irish in St. Augustine", undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Irish in the West Indies: Lecture at Maynooth College, Co. Kildare, Ireland, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Irish on Roanoke Island", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Irish Roots Magazine, 1992-2004 (Box 26, Folder 1-5)
  - Irish Times Columns, undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Irish in West Indies IGC Lecture/Aspects 3, 1997, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - "An Irishman's Diary" (From Research on Hurling and New York Cemetaries), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Newfoundland: The Most Irish Place Outside of Ireland", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Newfoundland: The Most Irish Place Outside of Ireland": Drafts, irishdiaspora.com, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "The South American Irish" (Brian McGinn), undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - South America Lecture and Notes, 1998 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - "St. Patrick's Day in New York 1779", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "St. Patrick's Day in Peru, 2004, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "St. Patrick's Day in Vienna", 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Venzuela's Irish Legacy, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Venezuela's Little Known Irish Legacy", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Vietnam: Articles, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 24A)
  - "Virginia's Lost Colonies", undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - West Indies: Lectures, 1976-1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series II: 18th Century Irish in New York, 1763-2000; 1.25 Linear Feet in 10 folders in a record carton, 17 folders in a second record carton, and 1 folder in a legal sized manuscript box.
  This series contains research materials about the Irish Disapora in 18th Century New York. The contents of this series include photocopies of articles and sometimes books, as well as bibliographic information used by McGinn for his research.
  - Catholic Church: Bishops, 1866-1999 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Catholic Church, Early History of: Rev J.R. Bayley, Henry de Courcy, 1856, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Catholic Churches: New York City, 1899-1999 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Catholic Churches of New York City: John Gilmary Shea ed., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Catholics in Early New York, 1963-1987 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Catholics: Michael Augustine Corrigan and the Shaping of Conservative Catholicism by Robert Emmett Curran, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Cemetaries, Burials, Gravesites I, 1863-1998 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cemetaries, Burials, Gravesites II, 1863-1998 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Cemetaries: "In Old New York: The Irish Dead in Trinity and St. Paul's Churchyards: by Michael J. O'Brien, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Cemetaries: MacNeven, Sampson, Tone, 1905-1998 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Friendly Sons of St. Patrick: History, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gaelic Athletic Association: History, 1980-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gaelic Athletic Association: Rule 21, 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Gaelic Sports: Newspaper clippings, 1987-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Henry George" by Charles Barker, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - History of Gaelic Sport: Hurling and Common, 1870-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hurling: 1871-1782: Thomas McMullin, 1763-1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hurling: "Caman: Two Thousand Years of Hurling in Ireland" by Art O'Madfabhail, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hurling: Seamus King, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ice Hocky and Hurling, 1944-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - New York - Music, 1992-2002 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - O'Sullivan, Timothy: Photographer, 1953-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - O'Sullivan, Timothy: Photographer- Civil War, 1869-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - St. Patrick's Day - United States I, 1779-1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - St. Patrick's Day - United States II, 1779-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - St. Patrick's Day: Newspaper Clippings (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - St. Patrick's Day: Non-United States, 1971-1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1988-1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series III: 16th and 17th Century America: Early Irish in America, 1574-2003; 2.34 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 3 folders in a second record carton, 13 folders in a third record carton, and 8 folders in a legal sized manuscript box.
  This series contains research materials about the Irish Disapora in 16th and 17th Century America. The contents of this series include photocopies of articles and sometimes books, as well as bibliographic information used by McGinn for his research.
  - 16th and 17th C Catholic Settlement, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Ann "Goody" Glover, 1994 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Audrey Lockhart 1660-1775 Emigration Biblio, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Brugger, Robert J. "Maryland: A Middle Temperament 1634-1980", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Colonial New York- Loyalists, Taverns, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cromwell and Virginia: Transportation 1655-1656 I, 1823-1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Cromwell and Virginia: Transportation 1655-1656 II, 1823-1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Glavin, Darby: Roanoke Voyager - Cuba, Spanish America I, 1918-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Glavin, Darby: Roanoke Voyager - Cuba, Spanish America II, 1918-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Glavin, Darby: Roanoke Voyager - Florida, 1907-1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Gookin, Daniel: Newport News, 1905-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Gookin, Daniel: Notes and Correspondence on, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gookin Family, 1991-1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Irish in America: 17th Century I, 1851-1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Irish in America: 17th Century II, 1851-1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Irish Maryland, 1904, 1935, 1968, 1974, 1981, 1987, 1994 (Box 27, Folder 4-5)
  - "Irish Nell" Butler Maryland 1681, 2001-2004 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Irish Poetry - 17th Century, 1851-1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Jamestown: Early Settlement, 1942-1999 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Jamestown: Maguire/Magner/Magnel, Francis, 1608-1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Jamestown: O'Conor, Dionis, 1929-1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Jamestown: Rediscovery Artifacts, 1974-2001 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Jamestown: Wingfield, Early Settlers, 1917-1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Jamestown and St. Mary's: Burned Cities of Romance" by Henry Chandlee Forman, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Maps: Irish in Virginia, 1933-1997 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - McCarty Family: Westmoreland Co. Kinsale?, 1968, 1993, 1998 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Meade Family: Virginia (18th Century), 1921-1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - McGlynn Research: Gilded Age, Clerical, Radicalism, Catholic Conservatism I, 1918-1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - McGlynn Research: Gilded Age, Clerical, Radicalism, Catholic Conservatism II, 1918-1991 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - McGlynn Research: Irish in America, 1956, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - McGlynn Research: McGlynn's original notes, 1991, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - McGlynn Research: Pictures (from published works, i.e. Illustrations), 1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newport News Virginia Settlement (in reference to Daniel Gookin), 1871-1987, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - O'Brien, Michael J. (1870-1960), 1907-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Population Studies Census: 17th & 18th C, 1980, 1994 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Reps, John W. "Tidewater Towns: City Planning in Colonial Virignia and Maryland", 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Rice: Limerick Merchants - Barbados, Virginia 1670s, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Roanoke Colony: Sir Ralph Lane, 1574-1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Roanoke Colony: Irish, 1578-2000 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Roanoke: Richard Butler, 1588-2003 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Roanoke: S.E. Morison, Gilbert and Recusants, 1908-1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Roanoke: Walter Raleigh, Richard Grenville, 1949-1969 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Company of London: Records, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Series IV: 18th and 19th Century Irish the United States, 1912; 2.52 Linear Feet in 5 legal sized manuscript boxes and 9 folders in an additional legal sized manuscript box.
  This series contains research materials about the Irish Disapora in the 18th and 19th Century United States. The contents of this series include photocopies of articles and sometimes books, as well as bibliographic information used by McGinn for his research.
  - 69th NY/165th Inf, 1969, 1990-1997 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - American Revolution Irish Loyalists, 1958, 1966, 1973, 1995 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Antietam Irish Brigade, 1983, 1994-1997 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Antietam: Priest, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Bibliography: U.S. Chronology, 1973-1983 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Black Irish, 1993-2001 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Celtic South, 1980-1986 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Cherokee - Irish, 1993-1996 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Civil War: Ella Lonn, 1969 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Civil War: TF Meagher, 1958, 1968, 1970-2001 (Box 20, Folder 10, Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Clinton Roots, 1966, 1990-1996 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Custer/Keogh/7th Cavalry/Little Bighorn, 1991, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Emigration 19th C, 1983-1985 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - French in American Revolution (Dillon and Walsh Regts), 1955-1957, 1986-1987 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Hibernia America: Dennis Clark, 1986 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Irish: 18th Century US Population (4.4 m?), 1981-1994 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Irish: American Press Catholic Periodicals, 1994-1998, 2001 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Irish in American Revolution, 1928, 1962, 1971-1975, 1982, 1991-1998 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
  - Irish BDE - Gettysburg, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Irish and Cinema/Film (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Irish: Civil War, 1957, 1969, 1975, 1993-1996, 2000-2001 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Irish Confederates, 1951-1952, 1997-2001 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Irish Language in U.S., 1984, 1992-2004 (Box 22, Folder 7, Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Irish: New York, 1993-2001 (Box 23, Folder 2-3)
  - Irish Quakers in U.S., 1966, 1971-1977, 1994-1996 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Irish: South Carolina, 1965-1985 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Irish in U.S., 1991-2001 (Box 23, Folder 6, Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Irish in U.S. Revolution (D.N. Doyle), 1981 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Irish: Washington, D.C., 1912-1922 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Journal of the West, 1992 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - "Martial Race," Irish AS, 2003-2005 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Matthias O'Conway Lexicographer, 1987-2004 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Meagher: Bibliography, 1997 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Melting Pot Soldiers (Civil War), 1988 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - MJO'B: Hidden Phase, 1919 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Mullens: Philadelphia (Thomas, Peggy), 1944, 1952-1955, 1962, 1997 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - "Not Forgetting the Land we Left: The Irish in Antebellum Richmond" (Normand C. McLeod, Jr.), 1998 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - The Tale of the War of 1812: Hemlock (Robert Sellar), 1918 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - U.S.: Irish Studies, 1998 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Presidents, 1993-1995 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - White Servitude in the Colony of Virginia (James Curtis Ballagh, A.B.), 1969 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Town Acts 18th C, 1935, 1950, 1969, 1972, 1996 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Volunteers of Ireland American Revolution, 1919, 1948-1949, 1955, 1962-1974, 1996-1999 (Box 25, Folder 8-9)
- Series V: Newfoundland (Nova Scotia, Canada), 1888-2004; 1.16 Linear Feet in 9 folders in a record carton, 14 folders in a second record carton, and 7 folders in a legal sized manuscript box.
  This series contains research materials about the Irish Diaspora in Newfoundland (Nova Scotia, Canada). The contents of this series include photocopies of articles and sometimes books, as well as bibliographic information used by McGinn for his research.
  - Anglo-Irish in Newfoundland, 1977-2004 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "Biddy," "Molly," "Sheila", 1938, 1977, 1990, 1998, 2000 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Canada/Newfoundland Irish Language, 1992-2000 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - D.B. Quinn: The Newfoundland, 1965 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Ecclesiastical History of Newfoundland, 1888-2004 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Faction Fighting; Hurling, 1982-2004 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Fishing and Fishing Terms, 1989-2004 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Gleaner Tales (Robert Sellar), 1895 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Irish Convicts in Newfoundland - Bob Reece, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Irish Culture, 1986-2004 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Irish in Canada: General, 1933-1985 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Irish in Newfoundland: General, 1967-2003 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Irish Language, 1979-2000 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Language: Dictionary of Newfoundland English: Irish Derived Words, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Lockhart, Audrey: Emigration to Newfoundland 17th and 18th Centuries, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - MacConmara Donnchadh Ruadh - Poet, 1999-2004 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Mannion, John, 1973-2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Meagher Family in Newfoundland, 1888, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Migration from Newfoundland, 1966-2001 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Na Geira, Sheila: Newfoundland Legend, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Nemec, Thomas F., 1972-1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Newfoundland: Bibliography, 2000-2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Newfoundland: Calvert Colony (Baltimore), 1976-1977, 1982, 1987 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Newfoundland: Maps, Illust., undated (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Newfoundland: Miscellaneous, 2001-2004 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Newfoundland: Outports, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Newfoundland: Prowse, D.W., 1896 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Newfoundland Studies: Table of Contents, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - United Irishmen in Newfoundland, 1799, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - The Untold Story: The Irish in Canada (Robert O'Driscoll and Lorna Reynolds), 1988 (Box 28, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Leeward Islands/Montserrat, 1642-2002; 2.13 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 7 folders in a second record carton, 21 folders in a third record carton, and 1 folder in a legal sized manuscript box.
  This series contains research materials about the Irish Diaspora in the Leeward Islands/Montserrat. The contents of this series include photocopies of articles and sometimes books, as well as bibliographic information used by McGinn for his research.
  - "Accessing the Usefulness of a Cartographic Curiosity: The 1673 Map of a Sugar Island", 1987 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Leeward Islands: "Development of the Leeward Islands Under the Restoration 1660-1688" S.S. Highman, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Leeward Islands: Kirwan Pedigree, 1997-2002 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Leeward Islands: Publications Images, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Montserrat: Berleant-Schiller Article on Labor and Economy, 1673-1989 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Montserrat: Bibliography, 1965-2002 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Montserrat: Blakes of Montserrat - Kerby Miller, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Montserrat: Blake Pedigree I, 1902-1996 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Montserrat: Blake Pedigree II, 1902-1996 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Montserrat: Brisket-Osborne Families (copies of 17th century correspondence), 1642, 1993-2000 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Montserrat: Bodkin Family, 1894, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Montserrat: Catholic Church, 1970-2000 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Montserrat: Census, 1654-1655 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Montserrat: Census, 1678-1679 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Montserrat: Census, 1719-1932 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Montserrat: Census, 1729-1730 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Montserrat: Cotter Family, 1956-1976 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Montserrat: Diary of John Baker: Barrister, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Montserrat: "The Early Years of Montserrat: A Chronicle of the People who Settled this Island. Somervill," Delores L., 1975 (Box 5, Folder 32)